all right
[Music]
yoga as therapy when is it helpful
as you've seen over the last few videos
the scientific literature on yoga is
limited in scope and quality
I talked about the long list of issues
that plague so many of the yoga trials
but let's continue down the list of
conditions to get a sense of the best
available balance of evidence for
example yoga as a therapy for irritable
bowel syndrome evidence from randomized
control trials found that yoga beat out
drugs and was equally effective as
moderate intensity walking so whichever
form of exercise you prefer what about
yoga for inflammatory bowel disease
since stress can be a trigger might yoga
help and a trial of yoga as an add-on
therapy for adolescents with
inflammatory bowel disease it didn't
seem to help at all but in a trial of
yoga versus written self-care advice for
adults with ulcerative colitis 12 weeks
of yoga induced a stronger increase in
quality of life and also reduced disease
activity even three months after the
study ended here's the graphs for
quality of life and disease activity
now the so-called self-care group was
really just handed a couple General
self-care books so the two treatments
yoga versus self-care were not matched
at all for time intensity uh feeling
part of a group or or for therapist
contact Each of which are likely to have
the yoga are more likely to
non-specifically improve their quality
of life so yes yoga might be effective
in improving quality of life and
ulcerative colitis however the benefits
may be no different to other group
exercise for example indeed there have
been 11 human studies on the influence
of moderate exercise programs upon
disease activity and chronic
inflammatory bowel disease and all 11
report benefit in terms of reduced
disease activity
using passive controls doesn't account
for expectancy effects attention given
to the study subjects and the time spent
the investment that the participants put
in here's an excellent example of why
having more active control groups is so
important
this details a series of studies on
non-pharmacological interventions for
menopausal hot flashes
for example randomized to eight weeks of
acupuncture eight weeks of sham
acupuncture or nothing just usual care
sham acupunctures when they still stick
needles in you but shallowly and not in
traditional acupuncture points there was
also a study of 10 weeks of yoga classes
or the attention control health and
wellness education classes which lasted
just as long as the yoga and were done
the same kind of group social setting
here's what they found the hot flashes
in the usual Care Group the the passive
control where they didn't do anything
special stayed pretty stable but the
real acupuncture worked way better but
so did the Sham acupuncture here's the
yoga
and here's the health and wellness
classes control group so yoga and
acupuncture both work just as well but
so did the non-yoga and fake acupuncture
there just appeared to be a general
placebo effect such that women in all
five intervention groups benefited
simply by being in a study that's why
it's always better to have the control
groups do something so you can have some
confidence at least some of the effect
of your intervention is real
but hey at least they had control groups
this study 12-minute Daily Yoga regimen
reverses osteoporotic bone loss caused
quite a stir
we know that when it comes to bone
health it's use it or lose it exercise
early and exercise often physical
activity is a widely accessible low-cost
and highly modifiable contributor to
bone health exercise transmits forces
through the skeleton generating signals
that are detected by your bone building
cells this is why the national
osteoporosis Foundation the
international osteoporosis foundation
and other agencies recommend
weight-bearing exercises for the
prevention of osteoporosis these include
high impact exercises such as jumping
aerobics and running as well as lower
impact exercises such as walking and
weight training to create these
mechanical signals that spark bone
growth lower impact activities such as
yoga are generally not considered bone
building that's why the results of this
study were so surprising it was a study
of Internet recruited volunteers
comparing bone mineral density changes
before and after yoga the researchers
devised a 12-minute DVD of 12 yoga poses
that they believed would stimulate
increased bone density in the spine and
both parts of the hip here are the Dozen
poses
and they appeared to get benefit in the
spine but not the hip but in the end out
of the 741 patients recruited at the
beginning only a few dozen actually sent
in their bone scans as instructed so
that's only like five percent right so
they lost 95 of the people that
originally started you can totally
imagine how those who got positive
results were more likely to send them in
and the others that failed just kind of
slunk away so I don't consider this
convincing evidence
now the authors had the attitude of hey
look so what do you got to lose the side
effects of yoga are all good so why not
give it a try
well what you have to lose is the
opportunity to do higher impact exercise
that has more decisive evidence of bone
benefit
and all the side effects are not
necessarily good
there have been vertebral compression
fractures associated with yoga in this
series of nine cases from the Mayo
Clinic they describe spinal compression
fractures occurring a month to years
after initiating yoga Associated spinal
flexion exercises both scientific and
media reports continue to advertise yoga
as a bone protective activity but
there's a need for selectivity in yoga
poses and populations that increased
fracture risk here's the yoga poses they
recommend
and these are the ones they encourage
people at risk to avoid and for the nine
patients developed a fracture in a
setting of normal or near normal bone
mineral density so maybe everyone should
be careful with these
yoga related injuries are not uncommon
resulting in thousands of emergency room
visits a year and approximately five
percent of those are coming in with
fractures I'll try to put that injury
rate in context comparing yoga to other
physical activities in my final video of
the yoga series next
foreign